Eastman Johnson
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Eastman Johnson letters
1851-1899
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Johnson, Eastman
12 items
The letters of Eastman Johnson contain 12 items and date from 1851 to 1899. The letters provide scattered documentation of his career as a painter and printmaker.
Biographical Note
American painter and printmaker Jonathan Eastman Johnson was born in Lovell, Maine in 1824. After apprenticing with a Boston lithographer, he moved to Washington D.C. in 1845 and became a portraitist of prominent Americans, including Daniel Webster and Dolly Madison. Beginning in 1849, Johnson spent two years at the Royal Academy in Dusseldorf, Germany, studying with Emanuel Leutze, and three years at The Hague. After returning to America in 1855, he settled in New York and focused on painting American genre subjects including Native Americans, African Americans, and farmers. He married Elizabeth Buckley in 1869, and they bought a home in Nantucket where he spent every summer for the rest of his life. After 1880, as the popularity of genre paintings declined, Johnson focused again on portraiture. He died in 1906.
Scope and Content Note
The letters of Eastman Johnson contain 12 items and date from 1851 to 1899. The letters provide scattered documentation of his career as a painter and printmaker.
The collection includes a letter to Mr. Champney concerning a painting by Eugene Benson, a letter to Charles Lanman, personal Secretary to Daniel Webster, a letter to Alfred Ordway, artist and Director of Paintings at the Boston Athenaeum, a letter to friend and patron John Coyle, and a letter to Mr. Cozzens concerning a painting which was already sold. Also found are two letters to artist and close friend Jervis McEntee, a letter to an unidentified Mrs. P, stating that he must go to Albany before starting another picture, a letter to Mr. Clark concerning a portrait, and a letter to Dr. Hochheimer regarding a print by Henry Wolf after one of Johnson's paintings. Also included in the collection is an oversize letter, written by Johnson in Dusseldorf, to his friend Charlotte Child, in which he speaks of his impressions of Germany, mutual friends, and working in Leutze's studio.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection, items are categorized into one series consisting of two folders. Items are arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Benson, Eugene, 1837-1908; Leutze, Emanuel, 1816-1868; Wolf, Henry, 1852-1916
Subjects-Topical:
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Portrait painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painting, Modern -- 19th century -- New York (State) -- New York
Names:
McEntee, Jervis, 1828-1891; Ordway, Alfred T., 1819-1897; Lanman, Charles, 1819-1895
Provenance
Items were donated in 1979 by Caroline Johnson Brown, Johnson's grand-niece, in 1976 by Letitia Howe, and by Charles E. Feinberg, an active donor to the Archives of American Art between 1955 and 1962, and were microfilmed after receipt.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.
Alternative Form Available
The collection was digitized in 2005 and is available via the Archives of American Art website.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Eastman Johnson Letters, 1851-1899, undated, Series 1:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  - Eastman Johnson Letters, 1851-1899, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Handwritten card, "What is called the 'line' of beauty", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To [Charles] Lanman, May 10, circa 1846, (with transcript) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Mr. Champney, March 4, circa 1870s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Mr. [Alfred] Ordway, June 3, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To [John] Coyle, March 13, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Mr. Cozzens, February 8, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Jervis [McEntee], October 12, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Jervis [McEntee], September 22, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Mrs. [P.?] (name illegible, photocopy), January 16, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Mr. Clark, June 3, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Dr. E. Hochheimer, April 20, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter to Charlotte [Child], March 25, 1851, (with transcript) (Box OV 2, Folder 1)